Chapter-09

1. Working of images in browser : Image element in browser are handeled a bit differently when compared to other elements in HTML.
For instance when a browser encounters a <h1> or <p> (tag) element in HTML, it just have to display those elements.

Where as, when a browser encounters an <img> element it first has to retrieve the image from its respective location in the web server & then display that element. 
Example : chit-chat-corner.html

2. Real time working of images in chit-chat-corner.html : 

a) Browser retrieves the file chit-chat-corner.html from the server.
b) After retrieving the file from the server, the browser reads the HTML file completely.
c) The browser first retrieves "pani-puri.jpg" image.
d) Later on the browser retrieves "masala-puri.jpg", "bhel-puri.jpg" & "sev-puri.jpg" images one after the other.

Note : This process of retrieving the image continues till the browser retrieves the final image of any html page.

Animation flow : 
Browser appears with sparkle effect.
Server & file appears simultaneously with sparkle effect.
Signal passes from browser to server & request : "I need chit-chat-corner.html file" appears.
Signal passes from server to browser & response : "Here is your file chit-chat-corner.html file" appears.
Signal passes from browser to server & request : "I need pani-puri.jpg" appears.
Signal passes from server to browser & response : "Here is your file pani-puri.jpg" appears.
(The last two point repeats till the final image is retrieved).

3. Image format used in web : 

There are basically three formats of images that we use in web : JPEG OR JPG, GIF, PNG.

a) JPG or JPEG(Joint Photographic Experts Group) is the most commonly used image format for photographic images.

JPEG is the image format most digital cameras use to save their photos.

Note : JPEG is the kind of format best used for continuous tone images like photographs. 

In order to save an image in the JPG format, we have to write the image name followed by '.jpg' extension.

For example : pani-puri.jpg

b) GIF or Graphic Interchange Format files are widely used for web graphics as they support only 256 colors. GIF files are typically small in size and very easily portable.

Note : In order to save an image in GIF format we have to write the image name followed by '.gif' extension.

For example : gifhy.gif

c) PNG or Portable Network Graphics are an image format originally designed to improve upon and replace the GIF format. PNG files are capable of handling upto 16 million colors, unlike only the 256 colors supported by GIF.

Note : In order to save an image in PNG format, we have to write the image name followed by '.png' extension.

For example : topper-tutorials.png

4. Difference b/w JPEG, GIF and PNG :

JPEG :

a) It is mainly used for photographs and complex colored images.
b) JPEG can represent 16 million different colors in images.
c) JPEG does not support transparency.
d) JPEG images are small in size.
e) JPEG does not support animation.

GIF : 

a) It is mainly used for limited color images such as graphs & logos.
b) GIF can represent 256 different colors only.
c) GIF supports transparency to an extent of only one solid color that can be set as transparent.
d) GIF images are larger in size compared to JPEG, but can be larger or smaller w.r.t number of colors used when compared to PNG.
e) GIF supports animation.

PNG :

a) It is mainly used for images which contain great amount of transparency, such as illustrations, logos & cliparts.
b) PNG can represent millions of different colors, & can be used in three different formats : PNG-8, PNG-24 & PNG-32 depending on the number of colors to be represented in an image.
c) PNG supports transparency to the extent of multiple solid colors that can be set as trasparent.
d) PNG images are larger in size compared to JPEG, but can be larger or smaller with respect to number of colors used when compared to GIF.
e) PNG does not support animation.

5. What is a pixel?
A. Pixel(Picture Element) is the smallest unit of an image or a computer screen.

A computer screen is made up of millions of dots called pixels.

Example : bird.jpg

a) Fully zoom on bird.jpg
b) Highlight single pixel and explain about it.
c) zoom back.

6. Bullet points :

a) Image element is used to place images in the web page.
b) Browser treat <img> element a little different compared to other html elements. The browser retrieves each image from web server one by one as & when it encounters an <img> element(tag) in a HTML page.
c) <img> element is an inline element and hence doesn't cause any line breaks in a web page.
d) The three widely supported image format by the web are : JPEG, PNG & GIF.
e) JPEG format is used for photographs or complex images.
f) GIF & PNG is used for logos, illustrations & cliparts or other simple graphics with few solid colors.
g) JPEG images can be compressed at a variety of different qualities, so we choose a best balance of quality & file size according to our needs.
h) GIF & PNG image formats allow you to make an image with the transparent background.
i) PNG has better transparency control than GIF & allows many more columns than GIF, which is limited only to 256 colors.
j) PNG has three different size option : PNG-8, PNG-24 & PNG-32 which can be used according to your needs.

7. Why do we call <img> element as a void element, eventhough it has a content?
A. HTML pages are purely based on text content & an image can never directly be a part of that HTML page, it is always considered as a separate entity.

8. when we load a web page, why don't we see the images loading one after the other?
A. The browser makes request for multiple images at the same time. Due to the speed of computers & networks, we see all our images loaded at a single time in our web page.

9. How do we differentiate between GIF & PNG?
A. GIF supports animation, but is only limited to 256 colors, where as PNG does not support animation, & can display millions of colors in a single image.

Based on the above points, we can differentiate b/w GIF & PNG  according to our needs.

10. What is the standard pixel ratio per inch?
A. Generally we use 72 pixels per inch as the standard. But according to the standards of css's pixels, it is considered to be 96 pixels per inch(ppi). 














     



















 









      
