Chapter-08

1. Introduction to DNS(Domain Name System) : Domain Name System or DNS is a server which acts as a Map for the website URL a.k.a the website name & the I/P addresses of its servers where our webpages are actually present.  

Example : www.brainsmartlabs.com (Where 'brainsmartlabs' is a domain name, '.com' is type of domain).

Domain Name : A Domain name is a name given to a website which points to a specific I/P addresses of a server which will be later Re-routed by the DNS.

A domain name is a simplified version of a server address as a end user cannot remember the I/P address of any server.

All domain names are controlled by a centralized organization called "Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers" (ICANN) to make sure that a particular domain name is not used by multiple users at a given instance of time.

2. Real time working of DNS : (Animation) 

a) Web browser appears with sparkle.
b) DNS server appears with sparkle.
c) Web server with cloud and wave signals appears.
d) First link appears from web broweser to DNS server, signal passes & 'What is the I/P of www.brainsmartlabs.com' request appears simultaniously.
e) Second link appears from DNS server to web browser, signal passes & 'Here is the I/P of 156.192.1.3' response appears simultaniously.
f) Third link appears from web browser to web server, signal passes & 'Request to server using I/P 156.192.1.3' request appears simultaniously.
g) Fourth link appears from web server to web browser, signal passes & 'Response from server to the browser' request appears simultaniously.

3. What is an I/P address : I/P address or Internet protocol address is a logical numeric address that is assigned to every system or computer.

Example : 156.192.1.3, 204.15.5.160, 204.15.5.128

4. What is an URL?
A. URL or Uniform Resource Locator is a global address that can be used to locate anything on the web including HTML pages, audio, video & many other forms of web content.

Example : http://www.brainsmartlabs.com

By specifying the location of the resource, An URL also names the protocol that helps to retrieve that resource.

In the above example we are using http protocol.

5. Introducing 'id' attribute : An 'id' attribute is used to uniquely identify an element (tag) in HTML.

'id' attribute is considered a Global attribute and hence can be a part of any HTML tag (element) such as <h1>,<p>,<title>,<a> etc..

'#' is a symbol used along with the id for us to exclusively display content from that particular element(tag) inside our HTML code.

6. Adding 'id' attribute to our index.html :

<html>
    <head>
        <title>Faculties</title>
        <style type="text/css">

            body{ 
                border: 4px double #379a33;
                padding: 30px;
                margin-left: 10%;
                margin-right: 10%;
                font-size: 20px;
                font-family:sans-serif;
                background-color:lavender;
                }
        </style>
    </head>
    <body>
        <h1>Founder</h1>
        <img src="../images/rajkumar.png" width="200" height="200">
        <h4>Dr.Rajkumar</h4>
        <p>Dr.Rajkumar, the founder of Topper Tutorials, armed with a vision of providing an academic environment that nurtured original thinking and created confident individuals he founded the Topper Tutorials in the year 2001.Being a fun loving person, he makes sure to spend time with his own children at home, listen to music & engage in different kinds of sports.</p>
        
        <h2 id ="faculty_members">Faculty members</h2>
             
        <img src="../images/shankarnag.png" width="200" height="220">
        
        <h4>Prof.Shankarnag</h4>
        <p>Prof.Shankarnag has been a faculty at Topper Tutorials since 2003.Outside of his responsibilities in the physics classroom and lab, he hosts sessions of physics to the young, observatory and voluntary students as a hobby.</p>

        <img src="../images/vishnuvardhan.png" width="200" height="195">
        <h4> Dr.Vishnuvardhan</h4>
        <p>Dr.Vishnuvardhan, Professor at Topper Tutorials began teaching in 2001. He currently teaches general, analytical, inorganic chemsitry and laboratory glassblowing.  He enjoys helping students, to reach their academic potential.  </p>

        <img src="../images/prabhakar.png" width="200" height="200">
        <h4>Asst.Prof.Prabhakar</h4>
        <p>Mr.Prabhakar Assistant Professor of Mathematics at Topper Tutorials began teaching in 2003. He has particularly mastered in the mathematical theory of knots, their applications and their connections with hyperbolic geometry.</p>

        <img src="../images/kashinath.png" width="200" height="180">
        <h4>Kashinath PhD</h4>
        <p>Prof.Kashinath, has been at Topper Tutorials since 2005. His teaching interests include plant systematics and genetics. Apart from biology, he advises in the areas of natural science, veterinary medicine, medical radiography and occupational therapy.</p>
        <p><a href = "../index.html">Back to Home</a></p>
    </body>
</html>



<html>
    <head>
    <title>Topper Tutorials</title>
        <style type="text/css">
        
            body{ 
            border: 4px double #379a33;
            padding: 30px;
            margin-left: 10%;
            margin-right: 10%;
            font-size: 20px;
            font-family:sans-serif;
            background-color:lavender;
            }
        </style>
    </head>
    <body>
        <img src="images/topper-tutorials-logo.png" width="200" height="200">
        <img src="images/font.png" width="800" height="120">
        <h2>"Right place for Bright Future"</h2>
        <img src="images/youth.png" width="600" height="280">
        <p>Topper Tutorials works towards "Nurturing Success of Every Student" through a friendly academic environment, supported by technology, which is built around a culture of caring.</p>
        
        <p>We achieve what we do through constant mentoring & observation. At the end of the course, our students will be fully enabled to do well in both board exams & competitive exams.</p>
        
        <h3>Our Faculty</h3>
        <p>An institution is only as good as its teachers are.  <a   href="staff/faculty.html#faculty_members" title="Description about  faculties of topper-tutorials ">Our faculty</a> members challenge their students, share insights gained through professional experience & communicate the knowledge they have acquired over the years through pure determination & grit. They are very supportive of their students in the classrooms & in the labs. <a target = "_blank" href="address/location.html" title = "Get the detailed directions of topper-tutorials">Locate Us.</a></p>
        
    </body>
</html> 

a) In faculty.html focus on <h2> Faculty members </h2>.
b) Add 'id' attribute inside <h2> tag ( <h2 id = "faculty_members"> Faculty members</h2>) type ani.
c) Cam zoom back.
d) Open index.html file.
e) Cam focus on <a> tag (inside first <a> tag).
f) Add #faculty_members inside <a> tag.(<a href = "staff/faculty.html #faculty_members"></a>).
g) Cam zoom back.
h) Show the output.
i) In output click on our faculty link.
j) Show the output.(In output page starts faculty members)
k) Scroll up & show (explain).
l) Scroll down back to original.

7. Introduction to 'target' attribute : 'target' attribute in HTML is written inside the <a> tag & is primarily used by the browser to open a specific window.

The value of the 'target' attribute tells the browser the 'target window' for the webpage.

If we use '_blank' as a value for the target attribute, the browser will always open in a new window to display the page.

Example : <a target = "_blank" href = "address/location.html">

8. Adding 'target' attribute to our index.html : 

a) In index.html focus on 2nd <a> tag.
b) Add target = "_blank" for index.html(<a target = "_blank" href = "address/location.html">) type ani.
c) Zoom back.
d) Show output.
e) In output click on 'Locate us'.
f) Locate us window will open in new tab.
g) Address will get displayed on the web page.

9. Introduction to 'title' attribute : A 'title' attribute is used to specify a relevant discription about the particular link.

'title' attribute can be used inside any tag.

When the cursor hovers over a particular link, a discription will be displayed below the link.

Note : 'title' in the <a> tag is just an attribute & it is generally used inside the <a> tag. Where as <title> is a tag which is used only inside the <head> element.

The value of 'title' attribute will always be in the form of 'text description'. 

10. Adding 'title' attribute to our index.html : 

a) In index.html focus on first <a> tag. (<a href = "staff/faculty.html #faculty_members">our faculty</a>).
b) Add 'title' attribute to the <a> tag.(<a href = "staff/faculty.html #faculty_members" title =  "Description about faculties of topper-tutorials">our faculty</a>) type ani.
c) Cam pans down & focus on 2nd <a> tag. (<a target = "_blank" href = "address/location.html"> Locate us</a>) type ani.
d) Add 'title' attribute to 2nd <a> tag.(<a target = "_blank" href = "address/location.html" title =  "Get the detailed description of topper-tutorials">Locate us</a>) type ani.
e) Zoom back & show the output.
f) In output, when your cursor hovers on 'Our faculty' link, the above given description will be displayed below the link.
g) When mouse hovers on 'Locate us' link the above given description will be displayed below the link.

11. Bullet points : 

a) A domain name is a unique name which is used to identify a website for example (brainsmartlabs.com).
b) An URL is a uniform resource locator or web address that is used to identify any resource.
c) You can use relative paths or URLs inside your <a> element's href attirbute to link with other web pages.
d) 'id' attribute is used to create destination in a page. # followed by the destination id is used to link to that location in a web page.
e) Use the 'title' attribute to provide a description of the link in <a> element.
f) Use the 'target' attribute to open a link in another browser tab.

12. How to find whether the domain names are unique or not?
A. Domain names are always unique as it is provided by the organization ICANN. which makes sures that a given domain name is unique.

13. Can the HTML files be edited directly on the web server?
A. It can be done, but we don't recommand you to edit directly on the web server as many users would have alredy viewed it.

14. How many ways are there to link two web pages?
A. There are two ways to link the web pages. they are : a) URLs b) Relative paths.

Where in, relative path can only be used to link two pages within the same website. while URLs are used to link other websites.


15. When we have two attributes inside one element is the order important?
A. No, the order doesn't matter when we have multiple attributes in a single element.

16. How to add 'title' for other elements apart from an <a> element?
A. You can add 'title' attribute to any element. If you have to add a 'title' attribute to a paragraph element, you have to write <p title = "Read the page"> </p>.  


 