Chapter-07

1. Nesting in HTML : Nesting in HTML is used to describe the placement or position of one or more elements within another element.

(Show tree diagram)

a) Here <html> tag represents root of the tree & it has two nested elements <head> tag & <body> tag, Hence <html> is considered the 'root' while <head> & <body> are the branches of the tree.
b) <title> is nested within the <head> element. So <title> is a branch of <head> & <head> is a branch of <html>.
c) <p> tag is nested inside the <body> element, so <p> tag is a branch of <body> & <body> is a branch of <html>.
d) <q> & <em> tags are nested inside <p>  element, so <q> & <em> are branches of <p> & <p> is a branch of <body> & <body> is a branch of <html>.

2. Introducing <li> element : 
 Lists or <li> tag in HTML are used to display a group of information in a sequentional order.
 
a) In order to create a list in HTML you have to write the content in between a <li> tag(opening tag) & </li> (closing tag).

Note: Inside a <li> you can place a paragraph, line breaks, images etc. you can also place an entire list inside another list element to create a nested list.

3. Adding <li> tag to : index.html

<html>
    <head>
        <title> Ammu's Kitchen </title>
        <style type="text/css">

            body{ 
                border: 4px dashed black;
                padding: 30px;
                margin-left: 10%;
                margin-right: 10%;
                font-size: 20px;
                font-family:sans-serif;
                background-color:#96ccad;
            }
            h1{
                text-align: center;
            }
        </style>
    </head>
    <body>
        <img src="images/ammus-kitchen-logo.png" height="200" width="1200">
        <h1>Welcome to Ammu's Kitchen</h1>

        <h2>Aloo paratha</h2>
        <img src="images/aloo-paratha.jpg"  height="200" width="300">
        <p> Aloo paratha is one of the most popular <em>Indian</em> breakfast. It consist of dough which is stuffed with a mixture of mashed potatos and spices. <q>Aloo paratha in Northern India is usually served with butter, curd and pickles.</q>
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <ol>
            <li>250 gm wheat flour</li>
            <li>1 cup water</li>
            <li>50 ml oil</li>
            <li>500 gm potatoes</li>
            <li>coriander leaves</li>
            <li>ginger garlic paste</li>
            <li>75 gm onions</li>
            <li>10 to 15 green chillies</li>
            <li>chilli powder & pinch of salt</li>
            <li>10 ml lime juice</li>
        </ol>

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <ul>
            <li>Make a soft dough by mixing wheat flour and a cup of water.</li>
            <li>Divide the dough into seperate balls, as per the size required .</li>
            <li>Boil the potatoes & remove its skin to mash it.</li>
            <li>Add the rest of the ingredients to the mashed potatoes and mix it well.</li>
            <li>Take each portion of the dough, flatten it on the palm. Stuff the filling in the dough and roll it again.</li>
            <li>Flatten the balls into 1/2 inch thick round parathas using a rolling pin.</li>
            <li>Heat a pan with a little oil on a medium flame. Cook the parathas until both sides are golden brown.</li>
            <li>Hot Aloo parathas are ready to serve </li>
        </ul>

        <h2>Mysore Rasam</h2>
        <img src="images/mysore-rasam.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p><q>Mysore Rasam is a South Indian main course usually served with rice</q>. It is traditionally prepared  using Tamarind Juice. This Rasam is originated from the Royal city of Mysore, hence it is named as <em>'Mysore Rasam'.</em> 
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <ol>
            <li> Small sized Tamarind</li>
            <li>Two Tamotoes</li>
            <li>Two teaspoons of Channa Dal & Bengal Gram</li>
            <li>Two tablespoon of Coriander seeds</li>
            <li>Two tablespoon of Toor Dal</li>
            <li>1/4 teaspoon of Pepper & Cumin seeds</li>
            <li>Three Red Chillies</li>
            <li>One teaspoon of Mustard seeds</li>
            <li>Two spoons of Ghee</li>
            <li>Few Curry leaves and Coriander leaves</li>
            <li>1/4 teaspoon of Hing</li>
            <li>Salt to taste</li>
        </ol>

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <ul>
            <li>Pressure cook the Toor dal, smash it and keep it aside.</li>
            <li>Soak tamarind in water and extract the juice. Pour it into a heavy bottomed vessel. </li>
            <li> Add chopped tomatoes to the extracted tamarind juice and keep it on the flame. Add hing and let the mixture boil till the raw smell of tamarind goes away</li>
            <li>Take a mini sauce pan and keep in on flame. Add oil , red chillies, coriander seeds, channa dal to fry it till the dal turns golden brown.</li>
            <li>Grind the above mixture with pepper seeds till it become a powder.</li>
            <li>Now inside the vessle: When the raw smell of tamarind goes away, add the smashed dal and adjust the water content. Add salt to taste and Boil the mixture till the arival of froth. Turn off the flame as the mixture is boiled sufficiently</li>
            <li>Add the grounded rasam powder prepared and mix it well.</li>
            <li>For Seasoning: In a separate pan, heat two spoons Ghee to a cetain degree. Add mustard seeds, broken dry red chilli and fry for 10 seconds.</li>            <li>Add broken curry leaves and fry it for a copule of seconds .</li>
            <li>Mix this seasoniong with the rasam. Garnish it  with fresh coriander leaves.</li>
            <li>Healthy Mysore Rasam is ready to taste.</li>
        </ul>

        <h2>Maggie Pakoda</h2>
        <img src="images/maggie-pakoda.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p>Maggie Pakoda is very easy and a quick snack recipe which is loved by both kids and adults. <q> It is usually served with tomato ketchup or chilli sauce.</q>
        </p>
        <h4>Ingredients</h4>
        <ol>
            <li>Maggi – 2 packets</li>
            <li>Water – 1 cup</li>
            <li>⅓ cup, finely chopped onions,cabbage & capsicum</li>
            <li>Three finely chopped Green chilies</li>
            <li>Ginger Garlic paste</li>
            <li>¼ cup Besan flour</li>
            <li>Three tablespoon of Rice flour</li>
            <li>1/4 cup of coriander leaves</li>
            <li>Oil to fry</li>
            <li>Salt to taste</li>
        </ol>

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <ul>
            <li>Combine water and Maggi Masala in a Bowl & start boiling it.</li>
            <li>Add the Maggi noodles to above mixture and allow it to cook.</li>
            <li>The water should evaporate completely for the noodles to be cooked atleast for 80% .</li>
            <li>Take another bowl and add besan flour, rice flour, cabbage, onion, capsicum, green chilies, ginger-garlic, coriander leaves, and salt in a bowl. Mix it well.</li>
            <li>Add the boiled Maggi noodles and mix everything very gently without mashing the Maggi noodles. Add 2-3 tablespoon of water, 1 tabelspoon at a time to bring the mixture together.</li>
            <li>Divide the mixture into 18 seperate portions. Rub the palm with some oil and shape each portion like a ball and flatten it slightly.</li>
            <li>Heat the oil to about 200°C. Carefully drop in some Maggi Mixture and fry it till it becomes golden brown and crunchy.
            <li>Stain the pakodas well and put them on a tissue paper.</li>
            <li>Spicy Maggie Pakodas is ready to serve.</li>
        </ul>
    </body>
</html>

a) Cam focus on Aloo Paratha ingredients section
b) remove <p> & </p> tags. Using multiple cursors remove <br> tags & show output.
c) Add <li>, </li> for Aloo Paratha ingredients paragraph one by one (Type Ani).
d) Zoom back & show the output.
e) In output focus on ingredients lists section.
f) Similarly, In Aloo Paratha method of preparation paragraph we have replaced <p> tag with <li>, </li> tags (opening and closing <li> tags appear with sparkle effect). 
g) Like wise, In Mysore Rasam, Ingrediants & Method of Preparation paragraph, we have replaced <p> tag with <li> tag (Opening & closing 'li' tags appear with sparkle effect).
h) In maggie pakoda Ingredients & Method of preparation paragraph, we have replaced <p> tag with <li> tag (opening & closing 'li' tags appear with sparkle effect).
i) Show the output.
j) In output, focus on all ingredients and method of preparation paragraph.


4. Types of lists in HTML : There are two types of lists in HTML 

a) Unordered list (<ul>) 
b) Ordered list (<ol>)

Unordered list (<ul>) : Unordered list in HTML is a block element which is used to group a list of related items, which doesn't have any particular order.

The list items of unordered list in HTML is by default marked with bullet points (.).

Ordered list (<ol>): Ordered list in HTML is a block element which is used to group a list of related items, which is displayed in a specific order by the browser.

The list items of ordered list in HTML is by default marked with numbers (1,2,3,...).

Note : 
a) The <ul> & <ol> tags in HTML are always used along with the <li> tag.
b) If you do not specify wheather it is ordered or unordered list, The browser by default considers it as an unordered list & displays it with bullet points.

5. Adding ordered list <ol> to the file index.html :

a) Cam focus on aloo paratha ingredient section <ol> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag).
b) Cam pans down </ol> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
c) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
d) Zoom back & show the output, In output focus on ordered list section & zoom back.
e) Cam focus on Mysore Rasam section <ol> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag of that section).
f) Cam pans down </ol> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
g) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
h) Cam focus on Maggie pakoda ingredient section <ol> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag of that section).
i) Cam pans down </ol> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
j) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
k) Zoom back & show the output.

6. Adding unordered list <ul> to the file index.html

a) Cam focus on aloo paratha Method of preparation section <ul> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag).
b) Cam pans down </ul> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
c) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
d) Zoom back & show the output, In output focus on unordered list section & zoom back.
e) Cam focus on Mysore Rasam Method of preparation section <ul> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag of that section).
f) Cam pans down </ul> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
g) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
h) Cam focus on Maggie pakoda Method of preparation section <ul> (Opening tag) appears with sparkle effect (above first <li> tag of that section).
i) Cam pans down </ul> (closing tag) appears with sparkle effect (below the last </li> tag of that section).
j) Indentation (Ctrl + Alt + I)
k) Zoom back & show the output.

7. Character entities in HTML : Character entities HTML are special characters which have some specific meaning when used in a HTML document.

For example : You cannot use the greater than (>) & lesser than (<) signs within your html text because the browsers will consider them to be tags.

Some character entities in HTML are :

&lt; : lesser than
&gt; : Greater than
&amp; : Ampersand

'&' (Ampersand) is the first character of any entity, so it cannot be used in your entity name.
If you need '&' (Ampersand) in your HTML content use '&amp;'.

8. Bullet Points :

a) Nested elements are those elements, which are placed completely inside other elements.
b) Only if your elements are nested properly, all your tags will match correctly.
c) HTML lists contains combination of two elements, <ol> with <li> tag for ordered list or <ul> with <li> for unordered list.
d) The browser by default creates the numbers for an ordered lists & it should not be added explicitly.
e) By adding <ol> or <ul> inside <li> element, A nested list can be created.
f) Use character entities for special characters like &, < and > in your HTML content.

9. Should <ol> or <ul> elements always be used with <li> tag elements?
A. Yes, you should use <ol> or <ul> elements always with your <li> element as <li> is used to identify each item & <ol> or <ul> element is used to group them together.

10. Can i place a <p> tag element or any other element inside an <ol> or <ul> element?
A. No, you cannot place <p> element or any other element inside an <ol> or <ul> element, because it is designed specifically to work only with the <li> element.

11. Can i place one list iniside another list?
A. Yes, you can place one list inside another. you just have to place an <ol> or an <ul> element inside a <li> element & this process is called as nested list.

