Chapter-06

1. Designing a HTML web page layout : Ammu's Kitchen

a) Create a rough sketch for our web page Ammu's kitchen.
b) Use the basic building blocks of HTML (<h1>,<h2>,<h4>,<img>,<p> & so on). To translate sketch into an outline for the HTML page.
c) Once you have the outline, then you can translate it into real HTML.
d) As we have the basic layout of HTML web page, We can add some new HTML elements to refer the web page.
e) Explain about rough sketch in detail.

2. Real time HTML web page creation : Ammu's kitchen

<html>
    <head>
        <title> Ammu's Kitchen </title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <img src="images/ammus-kitchen-logo.png" height="200" width="1200">
        <h1>Welcome to Ammu's Kitchen</h1>

        <h2>Aloo paratha</h2>
        <img src="images/aloo-paratha.jpg"  height="200" width="300">
        <p> Aloo paratha is one of the most popular Indian breakfast. It consist of dough which is stuffed with a mixture of mashed potatos and spices. Aloo paratha in Northern India is usually served with butter, curd and pickles.
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <p>250 gm wheat flour,1 cup water,50 ml oil,500 gm potatoes,coriander leaves,ginger garlic paste,75 gm onions,10 to 15 green chillies,chilli powder & pinch of salt,10 ml lime juice.</p>
            
 
        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Make a soft dough by mixing wheat flour and a cup of water. Divide the dough into seperate balls, as per the size required .Boil the potatoes & remove its skin to mash it,Add the rest of the ingredients to the mashed potatoes and mix it well.Take each portion of the dough, flatten it on the palm. Stuff the filling in the dough and roll it again. Flatten the balls into 1/2 inch thick round parathas using a rolling pin.Heat a pan with a little oil on a medium flame. Cook the parathas until both sides are golden brown. Hot Aloo parathas are ready to serve </p>
            
        <h2>Mysore Rasam</h2>
        <img src="images/mysore-rasam.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p>Mysore Rasam is a South Indian main course usually served with rice.It is traditionally prepared  using Tamarind Juice. This Rasam is originated from the Royal city of Mysore, hence it is named as 'Mysore Rasam'.
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <p>Small sized Tamarind,Two Tamotoes,Two teaspoons of Channa Dal & Bengal Gram,Two tablespoon of Coriander seeds,Two tablespoon of Toor Dal,1/4 teaspoon of Pepper & Cumin seeds,Three Red Chillies,One teaspoon of Mustard seeds,Two spoons of Ghee,Few Curry leaves and Coriander leaves,1/4 teaspoon of Hing,Salt to taste</p>
            

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Pressure cook the Toor dal, smash it and keep it aside. Soak tamarind in water and extract the juice. Pour it into a heavy bottomed vessel. Add chopped tomatoes to the extracted tamarind juice and keep it on the flame. Add hing and let the mixture boil till the raw smell of tamarind goes away. Take a mini sauce pan and keep in on flame. Add oil , red chillies, coriander seeds, channa dal to fry it till the dal turns golden brown. Grind the above mixture with pepper seeds till it become a powder. Now inside the vessle: When the raw smell of tamarind goes away, add the smashed dal and adjust the water content. Add salt to taste and Boil the mixture till the arrival of froth. Turn off the flame as the mixture is boiled sufficiently. Add the grounded rasam powder prepared and mix it well. For Seasoning: In a separate pan, heat two spoons Ghee to a cetain degree. Add mustard seeds, broken dry red chilli and fry for 10 seconds. For Seasoning: In a separate pan, heat two spoons Ghee to a cetain degree. Add mustard seeds, broken dry red chilli and fry for 10 seconds. Add broken curry leaves and fry it for a copule of seconds . Mix this seasoniong with the rasam. Garnish it  with fresh coriander leaves. Healthy Mysore Rasam is ready to taste.   </p>
           

        <h2>Maggie Pakoda</h2>
        <img src="images/maggie-pakoda.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p>Maggie Pakoda is very easy and a quick snack recipe which is loved by both kids and adults. It is usually served with tomato ketchup or chilli sauce.
        </p>
        <h4>Ingredients</h4>
        <p>Maggi – 2 packets, Water – 1 cup, ⅓ cup, finely chopped onions,cabbage & capsicum, Three finely chopped Green chilies, Ginger Garlic paste, ¼ cup Besan flour, Three tablespoon of Rice flour, 1/4 cup of coriander leaves, Oil to fry, Salt to taste
        </p>

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Combine water and Maggi Masala in a Bowl & start boiling it. Add the Maggi noodles to above mixture and allow it to cook.  The water should evaporate completely for the noodles to be cooked atleast for 80%. Take another bowl and add besan flour, rice flour, cabbage, onion, capsicum, green chilies, ginger-garlic, coriander leaves, and salt in a bowl. Mix it well. Add the boiled Maggi noodles and mix everything very gently without mashing the Maggi noodles. Add 2-3 tablespoon of water, 1 tabelspoon at a time to bring the mixture together. Divide the mixture into 18 seperate portions. Rub the palm with some oil and shape each portion like a ball and flatten it slightly. Heat the oil to about 200°C. Carefully drop in some Maggi Mixture and fry it till it becomes golden brown and crunchy.  Stain the pakodas well and put them on a tissue paper. Spicy Maggie Pakodas is ready to serve. 
        </p>
            
    </body>
</html>

a) Speed type animation.
b) Show the output.
c) In index.html explain about all tags one after the other.

3. Adding style to our index.html : (Speed type Ani)

        <style type="text/css">

            body{ 
                border: 4px dashed black;
                padding: 30px;
                margin-left: 10%;
                margin-right: 10%;
                font-size: 20px;
                font-family:sans-serif;
                background-color:#96ccad;
            }
            h1{
                text-align: center;
            }
        </style>

a) Speed type animation.
b) Show the output.
c) Add the code to align the <h1> in the center.
d) Show the output.

4. Block Element : The Block Element in HTML is an element which always start on a new line & are displayed by default with a line break above & below them.

The Block Element in HTML are often used as major building blocks to build a web page.
Ex : <p>, <h1>, <li>, <ol>, <ul> etc..

5. Inline Element : An Inline Element in HTML is an element which doesn't start on a new line & continues to flow with the remaining content of that particular element.

Inline Element usually make-up small pieces of content in a HTML page.
Ex: <img>, <em>, <q>, <a> etc..

6. Difference between block element & inline element : 

Block Element
a) Always start on a new line.
b) Causes a line break above & below a particular element.
c) Are considered as major building blocks in a HTML page.
d) It can have multiple lines.
e) <p>, <h1> etc are called as block elements.

Inline Element
a) Doesn't start on a new line.
b) Doesn't cause any line breaks.
c) It makes-up just a small piece of content in a HTML page.
d) It contains single line.
e) <img>, <em>, <q> etc are called as inline elements.

7. Introducing <q> tag element : The <q> tag in HTML is an inline element which is used to enclose a short single line quotation.

The <q> element is generally used for short quotations only, As they don't require paragraph breaks.

Note : using a " " directly in your paragraph doesn't make it an actual quote.

The best reason is add a <q> tag in the web page instead of " " is that you can style the quotes whichever the way you want it to look like.

Usually <q> tag element in HTML is used to mention something specific.


8. Adding <q> tag element to our HTML web page : Ammu's Kitchen

<html>
    <head>
        <title> Ammu's Kitchen </title>
        <style type="text/css">

            body{ 
                border: 4px dashed black;
                padding: 30px;
                margin-left: 10%;
                margin-right: 10%;
                font-size: 20px;
                font-family:sans-serif;
                background-color:#96ccad;
            }
            h1{
                text-align: center;
            }
        </style>
    </head>
    <body>
        <img src="images/ammus-kitchen-logo.png" height="200" width="1200">
        <h1>Welcome to Ammu's Kitchen</h1>

        <h2>Aloo paratha</h2>
        <img src="images/aloo-paratha.jpg"  height="200" width="300">
        <p> Aloo paratha is one of the most popular <em>Indian</em> breakfast. It consist of dough which is stuffed with a mixture of mashed potatos and spices. <q>Aloo paratha in Northern India is usually served with butter, curd and pickles.</q>
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <p>250 gm wheat flour,<br>1 cup water,<br>50 ml oil,<br>500 gm potatoes,<br>coriander leaves,<br>ginger garlic paste,<br>75 gm onions,<br>10 to 15 green chillies,<br>chilli powder & pinch of salt,<br>10 ml lime juice.</p>
            

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Make a soft dough by mixing wheat flour and a cup of water. Divide the dough into seperate balls, as per the size required .Boil the potatoes & remove its skin to mash it,Add the rest of the ingredients to the mashed potatoes and mix it well.Take each portion of the dough, flatten it on the palm. Stuff the filling in the dough and roll it again. Flatten the balls into 1/2 inch thick round parathas using a rolling pin.Heat a pan with a little oil on a medium flame. Cook the parathas until both sides are golden brown. Hot Aloo parathas are ready to serve </p>
            
        <h2>Mysore Rasam</h2>
        <img src="images/mysore-rasam.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p><q>Mysore Rasam is a South Indian main course usually served with rice</q>.It is traditionally prepared  using Tamarind Juice. This Rasam is originated from the Royal city of Mysore, hence it is named as <em>'Mysore Rasam'.</em>
        </p>

        <h4>Ingredients</h4>    
        <p>Small sized Tamarind,Two Tamotoes,Two teaspoons of Channa Dal & Bengal Gram,Two tablespoon of Coriander seeds,Two tablespoon of Toor Dal,1/4 teaspoon of Pepper & Cumin seeds,Three Red Chillies,One teaspoon of Mustard seeds,Two spoons of Ghee,Few Curry leaves and Coriander leaves,1/4 teaspoon of Hing,Salt to taste</p>
            

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Pressure cook the Toor dal, smash it and keep it aside. Soak tamarind in water and extract the juice. Pour it into a heavy bottomed vessel. Add chopped tomatoes to the extracted tamarind juice and keep it on the flame. Add hing and let the mixture boil till the raw smell of tamarind goes away. Take a mini sauce pan and keep in on flame. Add oil , red chillies, coriander seeds, channa dal to fry it till the dal turns golden brown. Grind the above mixture with pepper seeds till it become a powder. Now inside the vessle: When the raw smell of tamarind goes away, add the smashed dal and adjust the water content. Add salt to taste and Boil the mixture till the arrival of froth. Turn off the flame as the mixture is boiled sufficiently. Add the grounded rasam powder prepared and mix it well. For Seasoning: In a separate pan, heat two spoons Ghee to a cetain degree. Add mustard seeds, broken dry red chilli and fry for 10 seconds. For Seasoning: In a separate pan, heat two spoons Ghee to a cetain degree. Add mustard seeds, broken dry red chilli and fry for 10 seconds. Add broken curry leaves and fry it for a copule of seconds . Mix this seasoniong with the rasam. Garnish it  with fresh coriander leaves. Healthy Mysore Rasam is ready to taste.   </p>
           

        <h2>Maggie Pakoda</h2>
        <img src="images/maggie-pakoda.jpg"  height="220" width="320">
        <p>Maggie Pakoda is very easy and a quick snack recipe which is loved by both kids and adults. <q>It is usually served with tomato ketchup or chilli sauce.</q>
        </p>
        <h4>Ingredients</h4>
        <p>Maggi – 2 packets, Water – 1 cup, ⅓ cup, finely chopped onions,cabbage & capsicum, Three finely chopped Green chilies, Ginger Garlic paste, ¼ cup Besan flour, Three tablespoon of Rice flour, 1/4 cup of coriander leaves, Oil to fry, Salt to taste
        </p>

        <h4>Method of preparation</h4>
        <p>Combine water and Maggi Masala in a Bowl & start boiling it. Add the Maggi noodles to above mixture and allow it to cook.  The water should evaporate completely for the noodles to be cooked atleast for 80%. Take another bowl and add besan flour, rice flour, cabbage, onion, capsicum, green chilies, ginger-garlic, coriander leaves, and salt in a bowl. Mix it well. Add the boiled Maggi noodles and mix everything very gently without mashing the Maggi noodles. Add 2-3 tablespoon of water, 1 tabelspoon at a time to bring the mixture together. Divide the mixture into 18 seperate portions. Rub the palm with some oil and shape each portion like a ball and flatten it slightly. Heat the oil to about 200°C. Carefully drop in some Maggi Mixture and fry it till it becomes golden brown and crunchy.  Stain the pakodas well and put them on a tissue paper. Spicy Maggie Pakodas is ready to serve. 
        </p>
            
    </body>
</html>

a) In index.html cam focus on aloo paratha paragraph add <q> tag element & close with </q>.(type ani)
b) Zoom back & show the output.
c) Cam moves down & focus on Mysore Rasam paragraph add <q> tag element & close with </q>.(type ani)
d) Cam moves down & focus on Maggie Pakoda paragraph add <q> tag element & close with </q>.(type ani)
e) Zoom back & show the output.

9. Introducing the <em> tag element : The <em> is an inline element which is used to enclose the text that has to be emphasised (displayed in Italics) in a particular paragraph.

Adding <em> tag element to our index.html : 

a) Cam focus on aloo paratha paragraph in that add <em> tag to the word Indian.
b) Cam pans down to mysore rasam paragraph in that add <em> tag to the word Mysore Rasam in the last line.
c) Zoom back & show the output.
d) In output focus on Italic word 'Indian' & 'Mysore Rasam'.
e) Zoom back.

10. Introducing <br> (break) tag element : The <br> tag is a void element which is used to create line breaks in paragraphs.

The <br> tag is useful while writing address or poems.

Note : The <br> tag element doesn't contain a </br> (closing tag) since it is a void element.

11. Adding <br> tag element to index.html : 

a) Cam focus on ingredient paragraph section & add <br> tag element to it using multiple cursors shorcut in bracket.
b) zoom back & show output.
c) In output focus on ingredient paragraph section & zoom back.

12. Bullet points :

a) Plan the structure of your web page, starting with your sketch then create an outline & finally wirte the HTML.
b) Always use the element that most closely matches the meaning of your content.
c) <p>, <h1>, <li>, <ol>, <ul> etc are all block elements & always cause line breaks above & below them.
d) <em>, <q>, <br>, etc are all inline elements that flows inline with the remaining content of that element without causing any line breaks.
e) <br> is a void element & it is used to insert your own line breaks.
f) Void element has only opening tag & doesn't have any content.

13. What is a purpose of <br> element?
A.  <br> element is used to insert your own line break in a paragraph.

14. Are there any void elements other than <br>?
A.  Yes, there are other void elements for example <img> is a void element. 

15. Can we make any element as a void element?
A.  No, we cannot make any element as a void element because, an element which has content cannot be considered as a void element. 

16. Why is <br> called a "void" element?
A. In general an element in HTML contains opening tag + content + closing tag. But <br> doesn't contain any content or a closing tag hence it is called as void element.

Eg : <h1>Welcome to Ammu's Kitchen </h1> is a proper HTML element as it contains opening tag + content + closing tag.

250 gm wheat flour,<br>1 cup water is a void element as it doesn't contain any content & closing tag.





